[MUSIC]
虛無為假
In this lecture we'll talk about which hypothesis you might want to test.
這一講要談科學研究測試的假設
In science, we often rely on null hypothesis significance testing, but
本課程談的科學研究依賴虛無假設檢定
there are also some people who say that testing the null is very boring,
不過也有人認為這種方法很沒意義
because the null is always false.
因為虛無代表不可能為真的事情
Is this criticism valid, and if so, which hypothesis might we want to test instead?
如果這樣的質疑有效，所有研究到底要檢定什麼假設
Let's take a look.
讓我們好好談一談
In science, we very often use a null-hypothesis significance test.
許多科學研究常使用虛無假設檢定
Is the data we have observed surprising, assuming that the null-hypothesis is true?
如果發現是顯著的，能不能說虛無假設為真？
This practice is also often criticized.
許多學者批評這樣的操作
One of the critics of this is Cohen who says, the null hypothesis,
其中一位批評者就是Cohen
taken literally, is always false in the real world.
他說虛無假設就字面上的意思
是現實中不可能存在之事
So if the null is always false, what's the big deal about rejecting it?
如果虛無的事物不會存在
何必要大費周章地拒絕它？
So is this really true?
這樣就會讓發現變成真實嗎？
Is the null hypothesis always false?
虛無假設一定是不存在的嗎？
Well, not really, sometimes with very large sample sizes,
其實不見得，如果有相當大的樣本數
some effects are pretty darn close to zero.
有的效果會變得相當接近0
We can take a look in the many labs data set.
我拿Many Labs專案的公開資料說明
Many labs project was a big replication study where 36 different
這項專案是36組實驗團隊合作
laboratories all replicated the same set of studies.
嘗試重現14項實驗結果
So here every line is a different study.
圖中每一條線代表一項實驗
And if we look at the bottom, we see that at least two of these studies with more
最下面的兩項研究都有超過5000位參與者資料
than 5,000 participants yield an effect size that is indistinguishable from 0.
再現結果的效果量幾乎等於0
Now the question is whether if we would continue to an infinite
進一步可以問如果持續收集無限大的資料
會不會看到統計顯著的結果
number of observations there will be a statistically significant effect.
進一步可以問如果持續收集無限大的資料
會不會看到統計顯著的結果
We don't really know, but
老實說沒人知道
it seems unlikely that this really matters in practice most of the time.
沒有一項研究的主持人會把這樣的問題當真
It's important to distinguish between one situation
更重要的是區分合理的虛無假設
where the null is a very reasonable hypothesis and
a situation where the null is not a very reasonable hypothesis.
與不合理的虛無假設
If we use random assignment to conditions and we successfully accomplish this,
使用隨機分派執行樣本分組時
then there's no reason to assume that there is a difference between two groups,
許多研究的預設是分組間沒有差異
unless the manipulation that we use in our experiment actually has an effect.
除非分組的操作能導致真正的效果
And if it's possible that the manipulation has no effect and
如果操作有可能是無效果
this is a question you're interested in, then we can test the null.
檢定這樣的"虛無"就能回答研究者的問題
However, we also sometimes test for measured variables.
但是有時候使用統計檢定的目的是測量變項
An example of a measured variable is gender.
一個耳熟能詳的例子是性別
People often enter the lab with a specific gender.
多數研究的參與者屬於特定性別
They have the same gender throughout their lives,
因為大多數人的生命裡維持一種性別
so it's not something that you can easily change.
不可能進行人為改變
If you want to look at differences between men and women, for
想要比較男女生的差異
example, then you cannot directly manipulate this.
是無法用隨機分派的
You can only measure this variable and look at the differences.
只能由收集到的資料測量性別差異
Now let's see why this matters.
變項能否操作有何值得注意之處
We can compare the effect of random assignment and
可以從比較Many Labs專案資料裡隨機分派變項
measured variables in the many labs data set.
與純測量變項的效果差異得知
Let's take a look at one manipulated condition.
就拿定錨與性別為例
In this case, we look at the anchoring condition people are randomly assigned.
定錨是隨機分派的操作
Now in anchoring, people receive either a high or a low number as a manipulation.
定錨的操作是分派大小數字給參與者
Then after that,
一段時間之後
they all mak the same estimate about something they're uncertain about.
估計某個不確定狀況的數值
And what the literature shows is that this estimate is influenced by the height
文獻數據顯示定錨數字大小會影響估計的答案
of the anchor.
If they first get a very high number,
分派到大數字的參與者
their judgment under uncertainty is increased a little bit.
傾向給出高估的數字
And if they get a very low number, then their estimate is slightly lower.
分派到小數字的參與者的估計則偏低
Now, we can take a look at whether being assigned to the high
透過資料分析可以了解
anchoring condition or the low anchoring condition
高定錨參與者的表現有沒有不同於
低定錨參與者
has an effect on any of the other tests that participants did.
高定錨參與者的表現有沒有不同於
低定錨參與者
So they did a lot of tests.
為此兩組參與者做了很多測試
I'll look at ten different outcomes and see whether the random assignment to
我拿其中十種測試的資料做分析
the anchoring condition has an effect on any of these other dependent variables.
看看定錨有沒有在其他依變項發生效果
We can also take a look at whether there are gender effects.
像是比較性別在這些測試的表現
If we do this, we see that the anchoring condition only has an effect on one
分析之後發現定錨的操作只在預期有效的測試結果
造成差異
specific dependent variable, the anchoring effect that it's intended to influence.
分析之後發現定錨的操作只在預期有效的測試結果
造成差異
However, if we look at gender effects in this dataset,
再看測試資料的性別差異
we see that 7 out of the 10 dependent variables here all show a gender effect.
會發現其中七種測試有性別差異
That's a very high number.
這數目超出預期
So why is this the case?
為何有此結果
We don't know.
沒人曉得
There are probably things that vary with gender
也許資料中有其他變項和性別共變
導致測試結果的差異
that also influence the other dependent variables that we're measuring.
也許資料中有其他變項和性別共變
導致測試結果的差異
Now in all these studies there are also manipulations, and
專案裡的所有研究都有操弄
these were the main interests in the test.
是預期對測試有效果的變項
But we see that gender effects are always present or very often present.
然而性別差異隨處可見
So whenever we have a measured variable,
如果研究有純測量變項
it might be less interesting to test the null.
效果是不是存在通常不是檢定重點
Very often the null is not true.
虛無通常代表不存在之事
It's not a very interesting thing to see.
也不是有興趣知道之事
So why is this the case?
那要如何看待像性別差異的結果？
There is systematic noise in your data.
這類結果通常是資料中的背景噪音
Lykken and Meehl call this the crud factor.
Lykken與Meehl稱之為無意義因子
As long as you measure enough observations, these systematic differences
只要資料夠多，這些因子都會呈現統計顯著結果
that are present in your data will always yield a statistically significant result.
Now remember that in the many labs projects there were
因為Many Labs專案有5000多位參與者
more than 5,000 participants.
So this is a very large data set.
基本上就是巨量資料
And these tiny,
這些細微的
systematic noises will lead to differences on your dependent variable.
背景噪音自然會造成依變項的差異
So these things are not completely interesting.
這些因子本來與研究者的問題無關
They might be, but it's very difficult to pinpoint the origin of these effects.
找到差異源頭的可能性相當低
It might be just some sort of noise you're not interested in.
較有可能是與重要資訊無關的噪音
So whenever we can manipulate the factor, the null might be more interesting, but in
可操作變項的"虛無假設"是真正有興趣的
these cases of measured variables, there's always the crud factor to keep in mind.
但是請記住純測量變項通常是無意義因子
So we can conclude that in principle, all models are wrong, but
至此我們可以說“所有模型都是錯的”
some models are useful.
“不過有些是有用的”
This is a statement by George Box.
出自George Box的名言
What he means is that you can have a model that can be a useful test.
意思是說任何研究必能找到做有意義檢定的模型
After randomization it's possible, so when you can randomly assign people to
隨機化是讓模型有用的關鍵
只要隨機分派參與者到各種情況
conditions, the null can be a useful and a true hypothesis that you're interested in.
“虛無”就有檢定有興趣的假設是否為真的用處
But without randomization, the alternative,
反過來說，沒有隨機化
saying that there is an effect is not a very bold prediction.
宣稱存在效果並非了不起的預測
There very often is an effect.
非隨機化的效果相當常見
If the null is rarely true,
如果虛無有一點存在的可能性
then refuting the null says very little about the truth of a theory.
拒絕虛無假設無助於分辨理論的真假
You have to make a better prediction.
先需要一個好的預測
You have to do something more than just testing the null hypothesis.
檢定必須有對立於虛無假設的預測才有意義
The null hypothesis itself is what we know as a very weak hypothesis.
虛無假設是相對較弱的預測
Let's give an example.
來看這個例子
If I predict that it will rain next year in April,
今天我預測明年四月會下雨
then that's not a very strong hypothesis.
這並非夠強的預測
It's very easy to say that this is true.
只要四月任何一天有下雨
This is going to happen.
這個預測都可以成真
And you won't be impressed if I make this prediction and it turns out to be true.
我的預測成真的話也沒有人覺得神奇
You can also make a strong prediction, have a strong hypothesis.
因此需要一個更強的預測及假設
If I say that it will rain 7 millimeters on April 2nd next year and
現在我說明年四月二號會下7公釐的雨量
it turns out that this prediction is true,
要證明預測為真
now that will get me a job as a very good weatherman.
需要一位優秀的氣象專家評斷
So null hypothesis significance testing rejects the null compared to
虛無假設顯著檢定的功用是剔除相對於
任何對立假設或預測的虛無假設
any alternative, any other prediction goals.
虛無假設顯著檢定的功用是剔除相對於
任何對立假設或預測的虛無假設
And that's not very exciting in some situations.
這種功用在某些情況並無太大幫助
In these situations,
拿天氣預測為例，通常是定量的預測
just as with the weather, you want to make a point prediction.
You want to say, this is what I predict.
你可以說“這就是我的預測”
I just don't predict an effect, but I can predict with my theory,
“我不只預測這樣的結果，而是根據我的理論”
which is pretty good, an effect of a specific size.
“推測會有這樣的雨量”
And if you can accomplish this, that's much more impressive.
如果真能如此，才算是值得注意的研究
So confirming strong hypotheses gives a theory greater verisimilitude,
驗證強假設可增加理論的“似真度”
and that's a very difficult word for something that's akin to truth likeness.
這個不常見的詞意指逼近事實的程度
It gets you money in the bank.
理論與資料的關係
This is a finding that will increase your confidence in the theory,
好比把錢存在銀行
存越多信用額度越高
and that's what you want.
好比把錢存在銀行
存越多信用額度越高
Now let's play a small game.
讓我們玩個小遊戲
I'll ask you what the rule is underlying the numbers that are presented
請猜猜有什麼規則讓這些數字秀出來
on the screen.
請猜猜有什麼潛規則讓這些數字秀出來
You see the numbers 2, 4, and 6.
現在有2,4,6
You can test the rule by naming any other number that you think will follow
你可以叫出任何一個可能是第四個的數字
來測試潛規則
the rule.
你可以叫出任何一個可能是第四個的數字
來測試潛規則
Come up with any number you want, and I will say, yes,
你的回答符合規則的話，我會說“是”
it follows the rule or no, it will not the follow the rule.
不符合規則的話，我會說“否”
Take a moment to think of any number you want.
暫停一下想個數字
Which number would you like to test?
你的回答是什麼呢？
Let's say that you come up with the number 8.
假如你的回答是8
This makes sense, right?
似乎是有規則的，對吧？
You see 2 and you add 2, you get 4, you add 2, you get 6, so
因為2加2是4，再加2是6
maybe this is the rule, just adding 2.
所以加2可能就是潛規則
So if you would test 8 I can say yes, that's a valid number.
我若回答8是正確的，
那就是合乎規則的有效答案
It follows the rule.
我若回答8是正確的，
那就是合乎規則的有效答案
You might have a different theory.
你也可能有另一種理論
You might say, well, maybe it's 4 plus the number that comes before it.
認為中間的4是代表2與6的差異
所以第四個可能是10
So then we have 4 and 2 and 6, and then the next number might be 10.
認為中間的4是代表2與6的差異
所以第四個可能是10
So, if you want to test the number 10, perfectly fine.
10也是一個很好的答案
Yes, it also follows the same rule.
這個數字也顯示一種規則
But you have not learned a lot.
但你無法因此獲得有用的資訊
Is this really the underlying rule?
潛規則真是如此嗎？
What would happen if you would say 7?
如果回答7又是怎樣呢？
Now, that's a very interesting question, because in this case,
這些回答點出一個很有趣的問題
you're not trying to confirm the rule that you have in your mind.
你做回答並不是要確認設想的潛規則
You're trying to disconfirm, falsify your prediction.
而是要推翻否證心裡的預測
If I say 7, or if you say 7, then I'd say yes, that's also following
如果7也得到正確的回應
the same rule because in this case, the rule might be increasing numbers.
表示只有第四個數字比前面大都符合潛規則
As long as the next number is an increasing number,
只要之後的數字都比前面大
it follows the rule that I have.
都符合我設定的潛規則
And you would never discover this if you just tried to confirm the idea that you
但若你只想測試心中的規則
你永遠不會發現
have in your head.
但若你只想測試心中的規則
你永遠不會發現
So whenever we do a study and we try to confirm our predictions,
同樣地為了確認預測而做的研究
then this confirmation bias can be a systematic error in inductive reasoning.
也會因"確證性偏誤"導致歸納的系統性誤差
You cannot learn whether your theory is actually true if you
如果只一心一意確證一種預測
將無法知道理論是否正確
only set out to confirm your predictions.
如果只一心一意確證一種預測
將無法知道理論是否正確
Instead, you should try to have stronger
所以應該以否證最強的預測為重點
theoretical predictions where one of your predictions can be falsified.
One way to do this is to set out test two competing predictions.
可行的方法是設定兩種相互競爭的假設
Either the one hypothesis is true or the other, but they can't both be true.
其中一種假設可能為真
但絕不可能兩者都為真
So when I find some data, I can say this is at least in line with the one theory
收集資料之後，要確認是否符合其中一種假設
but is not in line with the other theory.
並且不符合另一種假設
So this is already a more interesting comparison to make.
這樣的比較就能導致有意義的結論
This is known as strong inference,
這就是所謂的強推論
crucial experiments that can exclude one alternative hypothesis.
關鍵實驗通常能排除最不可能的假設
And this is a very good way to have scientific progress.
因此促成科學良性進展
According to Platt, who talks about strong inference,
Platt的這段話可提醒你如何設計
有效回答問題的研究
you should always ask yourself the question when you design a study.
Platt的這段話可提醒你如何設計
有效回答問題的研究
But what experiment could disprove your hypothesis?
“但是有什麼樣的實驗能否證假設？”
That's the main thing you should set out to do.
請隨時拿這句話出來提醒自己
Of course you might not feel like disproving all the nice ideas that you
當然這不是要你否證所有想到的點子
have, but for science this is a very good thing to set out to do.
保持這樣的精神才是做科學研究的基本態度
So we've seen that people sometimes criticize null hypothesis significance
因為虛無假設檢定的預測力不高
testing because it's a very weak prediction.
而招來一些學者的批評
Anything goes as long as the null is not true.
只要虛無非真，任何事都有可能發生
And when you don't have random assignment,
若不是採用隨機分派進行研究
even this idea of the null being true is not a very interesting hypothesis to make.
虛無假設就與真正想測試的想法無關
So you should try to set out to make strong predictions,
好研究應當設定強預測
test competing hypotheses whenever this is possible.
檢定任何相互競爭的假設
[MUSIC]
影片結束